Howard S. Liebengood Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Howard S. Liebengood Papers 1950-1982 1973-1981
MSS61575
Liebengood, Howard S. (Howard Scholer), 1942-2005
13,300 items
38 containers plus 1 classified
15.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer and United States Senate sergeant at arms. Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, speeches, reports, legislative proposals, research files, notebooks, travel materials, campaign materials, financial and legal papers, Senate floor statements, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other papers pertaining primarily to Liebengood's service on the minority staff of the United States Senate Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities, as minority staff director of the United States Senate Select Committee on Intelligence, and as legislative counsel to Senate minority leader Howard H. Baker.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Baker, Howard H., Jr. (Howard Henry), 1925-2014.; Baker, Howard H., Jr. (Howard Henry), 1925-2014. Howard H. Baker papers. 1975-1982.; Carter, Billy.; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963--Assassination.; Liebengood, Howard S. (Howard Scholer), 1942-2005.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.
Organizations
Strategic Arms Limitation Talks II.; United States. Central Intelligence Agency.; United States. Congress. Senate. Select Committee on Intelligence.; United States. Congress. Senate. Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.
Subjects
Abscam Bribery Scandal, 1980.; Arms control.; Intelligence service--United States.; Political corruption--United States.; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974.; Watergate Trial, Washington, D.C., 1973.
Places
Korea--Foreign relations--United States.; Libya--Foreign relations--United States.; Panama Canal (Panama)--History.; Panama--Foreign relations--United States.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Korea.; United States--Foreign relations--Libya.; United States--Foreign relations--Panama.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States--Politics and government--1974-1977.; United States--Politics and government--1977-1981.
Titles
Panama Canal Treaties (1977 September 7)
Occupations
Lawyers.; Sergeants at arms, U.S. Senate.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Howard S. Liebengood, lawyer and United States Senate sergeant at arms, were deposited in the Library of Congress by Liebengood in 1983.
Transfers
Sound recordings have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
Restrictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified items in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified material.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1942, Dec. 29 Born, Plymouth, Ind.
1964 Graduated Kansas State University, Manhattan, Kans.
1968 LL.B., Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tenn.
1968 1970 Served in military police corps, Fort Riley, Kans., and Vietnam; discharged with rank of captain.
1970 1973 Member of law firm Neal & Harwell, Nashville, Tenn.
1973 1974 Assistant minority counsel, United States Senate, Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities (commonly known as Watergate Committee)
1974 1975 Partner in law firm, Thompson, Liebengood & Crawford, Nashville, Tenn.
1975 1976 Consultant, United States Senate, Select Committee on Intelligence
1976 1977 Minority staff director, United States Senate, Select Committee on Intelligence
1977 1981 Legislative counsel to Senate minority leader, United States Senate
1981 1983 Sergeant at arms, United States Senate
1983 Accepted a position at the Tobacco Institute, Washington, D.C.
1984 Partner in lobbying firm, Gold & Liebengood, Washington, D.C.
1995 Became chief lobbyist for Philip Morris Cos. Inc.
2001 2003 Chief of staff, Senate office of Fred Thompson of Tennessee
2003 Became chief of staff of personal office of Senate Majority Leader Bill Frist of Tennessee
2005, Jan. 13 Died, Vienna, Va.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Howard Scholer Liebengood (1942-2005) span the years 1950-1982, with the bulk of items concentrated in the period 1973-1981, during which Liebengood worked for the United States Senate assisting Tennessee senator Howard H. Baker. The Liebengood Papers represent numerous aspects of Baker's work in the Senate, especially those activities involving Liebengood, and contain some of Baker's own correspondence and papers. Included are correspondence, office memoranda, reports, Senate papers, trip material, research items, speeches, campaign material, legislative proposals, notebooks, a few newspaper clippings and photographs, and miscellany. The papers are divided into five series created by Liebengood or his staff, and there is some topical overlap between the various series. Many original folder titles have been retained, and within each series, many folders have been grouped together by subject matter. The series consist of Howard H. Baker Files, Minority Leader's Office Files, Panama Canal Treaties Files, Senate Select Committee on Intelligence Files, Watergate Committee Files, and Classified.
Liebengood left Nashville, Tennessee, and arrived in Washington, D.C., during the summer of 1973 to work as part of the minority staff of the United States Senate Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities (commonly known as the Watergate Committee). Baker was the ranking Republican on the committee. Liebengood's responsibilities included interviewing potential witnesses. The Watergate Committee files include a large group of abstracts of interviews and testimony. Baker conducted a special investigation of the role of the Central Intelligence Agency in the Watergate break-in and related events. Much of the research material from the investigation is included in this series. A number security classified items were removed from this series and placed in the Classified series thatis described at the end of the container list.
After the Watergate hearings, Liebengood returned to private law practice. In 1975 he began working with the Senate Select Committee on Intelligence, first as a consultant and in 1976 as the minority staff director, a position he held for one year. Intelligence Committee files reflect some of the intelligence and security concerns of the period: the desire to define and restrict the scope of operations of the Central Intelligence Agency and the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the renewed investigation into President John F. Kennedy's assassination, and issues such as the Korean influence-buying scandal ("Koreagate") and the Strategic Arms Limitation Talks II (SALT II) being negotiated with the Soviet Union.
From March 1977 until January 1981, Liebengood served as Baker's legislative counsel in the minority leader's office. His papers for this period are the most numerous and wide-ranging in the collection. There are large sections on legislative proposals, nominations and appointments, Senate committees and Senate Republican groups, and official trips. Also included are sections on various issues that arose during President Jimmy Carter's administration, such as the Abscam bribery scandal, the scandal concerning his brother Billy Carter's ties to Libya, and the Strategic Arms Limitation Talks II.
Papers relating to the Panama Canal treaties have been separated from the Minority Leader's Office Files and placed in a separate series. The Senate debated the Panama Canal treaties in 1977-1978, and Baker was a central figure during the deliberations and final acceptance of the treaties. It was perhaps because of Baker's leadership that the treaties were ratified in 1978. Republican responses to the Panama Canal treaties reveal a split in the party between moderates who supported Baker and conservatives, such as Ronald Reagan, who felt that Baker had cooperated in a Panama Canal "give-away."
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in six series:
Howard H. Baker Files, 1975-1982
Minority Leader's Office Files, 1976-1982
Panama Canal Treaties Files, 1963-1982
Senate Select Committee on Intelligence Files, 1950-1982
Watergate Committee Files, 1971-1982
Classified, 1971-1980
Container List
- Howard H. Baker Files, 1975-1982 (Box 1-2)
  Primarily correspondence, but also legal papers, newspaper clippings, reports, and photographs. Includes material from Baker's 1980 presidential bid.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization, topic, or type of material.
  - Bull, Stephen, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
  - Dirksen, Louella, 1980
  - Dirksen Center, Pekin, Ill., 1979-1981
  - Ingram, Frederic, 1980, undated
  - Kansas State University, Alfred M. Landon lecture, Manhattan, Kans., 1976-1979, (2 folders)
  - Legal papers, 1980
  - Nashville Airport Authority, Nashville, Tenn., 1979-1980
  - National security proposals, 1979-1980
  - Nobel Peace Prize, nomination of W. Clement Stone, 1981
  - Office miscellany, 1981, undated, (2 folders)
  - Patestides, Michael, 1980
  - Personal business papers, 1979
  - Photographs, 1978
  - Presidential campaign
    - Blackwell, Steven, 1977-1979
    - Correspondence, 1976-1980, undated, (4 folders)
    - Legal file, 1979-1980, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Morgan, Edward P., 1979-1980
    - Puerto Rico, 1980
    - Miscellany, 1980
  - Secret Service, 1982
  - Senate election campaign, 1977-1978
  - Weizmann Institute, Rehovot, Israel, 1977-1979, undated, (3 folders)
  - Miscellany, 1975-1982
- Minority Leader's Office Files, 1976-1982 (Box 2-19)
  Correspondence, legislation, reports, Senate floor statements, financial materials, agendas, minutes of meetings, and trip material reflecting the broad range of Liebengood's activities in his role as legislative counsel to Senate minority leader Howard H. Baker.
  - Abscam Bribery Scandal (Box 2)
    - Briefing book, 1980
    - General, 1980
    - Pressler, Larry, 1980
  - Baker, Howard H.
    - Correspondence
      - Routine
        - 1979
        - 1980 (Box 3)
      - Senate and House of Representatives, 1978-1980, (2 folders)
      - Special, 1979-1980, (3 folders)
    - Floor statements, 1979, undated
    - Political material
      - General, 1979
      - Rhinelander, John, 1979
    - Schedules, 1979, (2 folders)
    - Senate legal papers, 1977-1980, (4 folders)
  - Carhart, Tom, 1982
  - Carlton Breakfast Group, 1979-1981
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, Washington, D.C.
    - 1978
    - 1979-1981 (Box 4)
  - Clinch River breeder reactor, Oak Ridge, Tenn., 1977-1979, (3 folders)
  - Congressional Award Program
    - Annual report, 1980
    - Board of directors
      - Meetings, 1980-1981, (2 folders)
      - Nominations, 1978-1980
    - Correspondence, 1979-1981, (4 folders)
    - Minnesota pilot project, 1979
    - Printed matter, 1979
    - Tax-exempt status, 1979-1980
    - Tulanian, David M., 1980 (Box 5)
    - Miscellany, 1979-1980
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1977
  - Cuba and Soviet troop presence, 1979
  - Culvahouse, A. B., 1977
  - Foreign policy, 1978-1979
  - Frye, Alton, 1978-1980
  - Hagel, Charles, 1978-1980
  - Harlowe, Bryce L., 1977-1980
  - Harmer, John, 1979-1981
  - Heidrich, George, 1981
  - Heiman, Richard, 1982
  - Hildenbrand, William, 1980
  - Huberty, Robert, 1980
  - Incumbency Watch, 1980
  - Intelligence, Central Intelligence Agency, 1978
  - Iranian situation, 1980
  - Joint leadership, 1977-1979, (2 folders)
  - Kellerman, Donald, 1979-1980
  - Koshrouani, Hasheem, 1981
  - Legislation
    - Chrysler Corp., 1979-1980
    - Election reform, 1977
    - Equal Rights Amendment, 1982
    - Energy, 1979
    - Federal Election Campaign Act, 1978
    - Federal Election Commission, 1978
    - Gasohol (Box 6)
      - "Alcohol: The Renewable Fuel From Our Nation's Resources," 1977
      - General, 1977-1978
    - Lock and Dam 26/User Fees, Mississippi River, 1978
    - Neighborhood revitalization, 1977
    - Nuclear nonproliferation, 1977-1978, (2 folders)
    - Republican Conference Energy Initiative, 1977
    - Second Concurrent Budget Resolution, 1979
  - Legislative counsel
    - Anti-Trust Equal Enforcement Act, 1979
    - Airlie Foundation, Warrenton, Va., 1978
    - Brazil's energy and alcohol program, 1978
    - "Catch 62" legislation, 1980
    - Constitutional convention, 1979
    - Correspondence
      - Jan.-June 1978, (2 folders)
      - July 1978-Aug. 1979, (10 folders) (Box 7)
      - Sept. 1979-Sept. 1980, (12 folders) (Box 8)
      - Oct.-Dec. 1980, undated, (4 folders) (Box 9)
    - Financial material, 1980
    - Government regulation, 1980
    - "Lame duck" sessions of Congress, 1980
    - Newspaper delivery and gas rationing, 1980
    - Presidential message, 1980
    - Reorganization, 1979
    - Reports, 1980
    - Resumes and applications, 1980
    - Senate rules and campaign finance laws, 1979
    - Tuition tax credits for private schools, 1978
    - Zweben, Murray, declaration in the Barry M. Goldwater lawsuit, 1979
    - Miscellany
      - 1977-1978, (2 folders)
      - 1979-1980, (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - Legislative scheduling, 1979
  - Libya and Billy Carter
    - Correspondence, 1980
    - Notes, 1979-1980
    - "Report of the President," 1980
    - Senate resolutions, 1980
    - Miscellany, 1980
  - Liebengood, Howard S.
    - Appointment calendars, 1978-1980, (3 folders)
    - Notes, 1978, undated (Box 11)
    - Personal file, 1980
    - Speeches, 1979, undated
    - Miscellany, 1980
  - Lobbyists, 1977-1982, (5 folders)
  - Manuel, Philip, 1980
  - Murphy, Beverly, 1979
  - Nominations and appointments
    - Arms Control and Disarmament Agency, 1977-1978
    - Civil Aeronautics Board, 1980
    - Commodity Futures Trading Commission, 1979-1980
    - Consumer Product Safety Commission, 1978-1979
    - Corporation for Public Broadcasting, 1980
    - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, 1979-1980
    - Federal Election Commission
      - General, 1979-1980
      - Reiche, Frank
        - Sept. 1978-May 1979
        - June 1979-Nov. 1980, undated, (4 folders) (Box 12)
    - Federal Home Loan Bank Board, 1978-1979
    - Federal Maritime Commission, 1979
    - Haig, Alexander Meigs, 1980-1981
    - International Trade Commission, 1979-1980
    - Interstate Commerce Commission, 1979-1980
    - John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, Washington, D.C., 1980
    - Judgeships, 1979-1980
    - McClaughry, John, 1977
    - National Credit Union Administration, 1979
    - National Energy Security Corporation, 1980
    - National Labor Relations Board, 1979-1980
    - Postal Rate Commission, 1980
    - Postal Service Board of Governors, 1979-1980
    - Securities and Exchange Commission, 1979-1980
    - Synthetic Fuels Corporation, 1980
    - Miscellany
      - Correspondence, 1977-1980
      - Malloy, Raymond J., 1978-1979 (Box 13)
      - Notes and resumes, 1979-1980
      - Pending before the Senate, 1980
  - Outdoor Advertising Association, 1979
  - Ranking minority members meetings
    - Agendas, 1978
    - Correspondence, 1978
    - Counsel and staff directors' meeting, 1978-1979
    - Minutes, 1978
    - Miscellany, 1978
  - Rash, Bryson, 1979
  - Reagan, Ronald, transition, 1980
  - Republican economic policy statement, 1979
  - Republican Policy Committee
    - Briefing for new legislative staff, 1978
    - Weekly luncheons
      - Jan.-May 1979, (2 folders)
      - June-Dec. 1979, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Miscellany, 1979
  - Rose, William E., 1979
  - Secret Service
    - Correspondence, 1979-1980, (2 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1979-1980
  - Senate
    - Committees
      - Ethics, 1977-1981, (3 folders)
      - Foreign relations
        - Report on North Atlantic Treaty Organization and Sweden, 1980
      - "Senate Perspective on Spain and the Middle East," 1981
        - Miscellany, 1978-1981, (3 folders)
      - Presidential Campaign Advisory Committee (Box 15)
        - Agenda, 1980
        - Miscellany, 1980
      - Rules, 1979
    - Legal counsel, Michael Davidson, 1980, (5 folders)
    - Reorganization
      - Committee budget requests, 1980
      - Correspondence, 1980
      - Miscellany, 1980
    - Rules changes (Box 16)
      - Byrd resolution, 1979
      - Miscellany, 1976-1979, undated, (4 folders)
  - Senators' legislative interests, 1979, (8 folders)
  - Special counsel to investigate loan transactions between the National Bank of Georgia and the Carter peanut warehouse, 1979
  - Strategic Arms Limitation Talks II (SALT II) (Box 17)
    - Baker, Howard H., statement, 1979
    - Correspondence, 1978-1980, (2 folders)
    - Printed matter, 1979
    - Miscellany, 1979
  - Trips
    - China
      - Background material, 1979
      - Correspondence, 1979
      - Itineraries and personnel, 1979
      - Miscellany, 1979
    - Europe
      - Background material, 1982
      - Correspondence, 1982
      - Financial material, 1982
      - Itineraries, 1982
      - Miscellany, 1979-1980
    - Greece
      - Background on Middle East, 1980
      - Correspondence, 1980
      - Financial material, 1980
      - Greek-Turkish issues, 1980
      - Itineraries, 1980 (Box 18)
      - Narcotics, 1980
      - Photographs, 1980
      - Staff delegation, Liebengood and George F. Murphy, 1980
      - Miscellany, 1980
    - Latin America
      - Congressional delegation, 1981-1982
      - Financial material, 1981-1982, (2 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1981-1982
    - Middle East
      - "Draft Codel Baker Report," 1981
      - Financial material
        - General, 1981
        - Individual forms, 1981
      - Itineraries and personnel, 1981
      - Miscellany, 1981
    - Northern Europe
      - Correspondence, 1980
      - Financial material, 1980
      - Miscellany, 1980
    - Soviet Union (Box 19)
      - Briefing book, 1978-1979
      - Correspondence, 1978-1979
      - Financial material
        - Baker, Howard H., expenses, 1979
        - Foreign currency expenditure forms, 1979
        - Liebengood, expenses, 1979
        - Miscellaneous, 1978-1979, (2 folders)
      - Itineraries and personnel, 1978-1979
      - Photographs, 1979
      - Press conferences, 1979
      - Soviet dissidents and Soviet Jewry, 1978
      - Miscellany, 1979
    - Miscellaneous, 1976-1979
  - Vietnam Veterans Memorial, Washington D.C., 1981
  - Wilkes, Lloyd, 1977-1982, (2 folders)
  - Miscellany, 1977-1980, undated
- Panama Canal Treaties Files, 1963-1982 (Box 20-29)
  Correspondence, reports, proposals for treaty amendments, Senate witness questions and statements, commentary from various political figures, speeches and floor statements, newspaper clippings, and trip materials. Almost all the material dates from the 1977-1978 debate over and ratification of the treaties.
  - Amendments (Box 20)
    - Baker, Howard H., consultants' proposals, 1977-1978
    - Notebook, 1978, (2 folders)
    - Miscellaneous, 1977-1978, undated, (2 folders)
  - Baker, Howard H.
    - Interviews, 1982, undated
    - Notebook
      - Parts 1-6, undated, (6 folders)
      - Appendix, undated
    - Senate floor statements, undated
  - Book proposal, 1978 (Box 21)
  - Constitutional issues
  - General, 1977-1978, (2 folders)
    - Notebook from Orrin Hatch, 1977, (4 folders)
  - Consultants
    - Besozzi, Paul C., 1971-1978
    - Fontaine, Roger W., 1977-1978
    - Rogers, William D., 1977-1978, undated, (5 folders)
  - Correspondence (Box 22)
    - Canal Zone residents, 1977
    - Carter, Jimmy, 1978
    - Ford, Gerald R., 1978
    - General, 1977-1982, (2 folders)
    - Liebengood, Howard S., reading file, 1978
    - Panamanian officials, 1977-1978
    - Senate, 1977-1978
    - Staff memoranda, 1977-1978, (4 folders)
    - Vance, Cyrus R., 1977-1978
  - Destler, I. M., "Learning from Panama," 1978
  - Drug trafficking investigations, 1977
  - Enabling legislation, 1978
  - Expropriation of property, 1977-1978
  - Flag display, 1977 (Box 23)
  - Floor debate, 1978, undated, (3 folders)
  - Foreign Broadcast Information Service, 1977-1978, (2 folders)
  - Foreign Relations Committee
    - Correspondence, 1977-1978, (3 folders)
    - Witnesses
      - Questions, undated, (2 folders)
      - Statements
        - "A-E" miscellaneous, 1977, (2 folders)
        - "F-H" miscellaneous, 1977 (Box 24)
        - Inserts from administration officials, 1977, (2 folders)
        - "J-W" miscellaneous, 1977, (4 folders)
  - Harman, Phillip
    - Correspondence
      - 1977-1980, (3 folders)
      - 1981-1982, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1978-1979, undated
    - Reports, 1977-1981, undated, (5 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1977-1978, undated
  - Helms, Jesse, 1978
  - Implementing legislation, 1979
  - Instruments of ratification, 1978
  - Law suit, 1978
  - Legal research papers (Box 26)
    - Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress, 1977
    - Miscellaneous, 1963, undated, (2 folders)
  - Maier, Harold G., report, 1977
  - Moss, Ambler, 1979-1982
  - Newspaper clippings
    - Panama, 1977
    - Tennessee
      - Articles, 1978
      - Editorials, 1978
    - Miscellaneous, 1977-1978
  - Panamanian government
    - Spanish language treaties, 1977
    - Miscellany, 1977
  - Political comments
    - "A-C" miscellaneous, 1977
    - Dole, Robert, 1977-1978
    - "D-I" miscellaneous, 1971-1978
    - "K-P" miscellaneous, 1977 (Box 27)
    - Reagan, Ronald, 1977-1978
    - "R-W" miscellaneous, 1977, undated
  - Republican Policy Committee report, 1977
  - Republican senators' views, 1977-1978, (2 folders)
  - Schmitt, Harrison, report, 1978
  - Sovereignty issue, 1977
  - Speeches
    - Liebengood, Howard S., 1978
    - Staff drafts, 1978
    - Miscellaneous, 1978, undated
  - State Department
    - "Analysis of the Estimated Cash Requirements of the Panama Canal Commission," 1978
    - Telegrams, 1978
  - State Department and White House information notebook, 1978
    - Parts 1-4, (4 folders)
    - Part 5 (Box 28)
  - Tambs, Lewis A., 1978
  - Tennessee opinion survey, 1977-1978
  - Trips
    - Latin America
      - Atomic energy programs, 1977-1978
      - Background material, 1978
      - Chamber of Commerce of Panama, 1978
      - Correspondence, 1978
      - Financial material
        - General, 1978
        - Receipts
          - Baker, Howard H., 1978
          - Delegation, 1978
          - Liebengood, Howard S., 1978
      - Itineraries and local arrangements, 1978
      - Meetings in Panama, 1978
      - Newspaper clippings, 1978
      - Notebook, 1978
        - Part 1
        - Parts 2-4, (3 folders) (Box 29)
      - Photographs, 1978
      - Printed matter, 1978
      - Trip reports, 1978
      - Miscellany, 1978
    - Panama
      - Itinerary and local arrangements, 1977
      - Newspaper clippings, 1977
      - Notebook, 1977, (2 folders)
      - Notes, 1977
      - Miscellany, 1977
  - White House
    - Meeting, 1978
    - Press release, 1977
  - Miscellaneous
    - Notes, undated
    - Printed matter, 1977, undated
    - Reports and statements, 1977-1978, undated
- Senate Select Committee on Intelligence Files, 1950-1982 (Box 30-35)